Hi, everyone.
Let's get started.
In the last couple
of lectures, we've
been talking about
training RL and imitation
learning systems that can
do multiple different tasks.
And we first looked at this from
the lens of multi-task imitation
and reinforcement
learning, where
you condition a policy or a
Q-function not just on the state
but also on some sort of
descriptor of the task,
or where there
are also scenarios
in the goal condition setting
where that descriptor could
actually be a state
itself, like a goal state
that you're trying to reach.
And then more recently,
we were talking
about meta-reinforcement
learning, where you could think
of that instead of conditioning
on a description of the task,
you want to do-- you
actually need to figure out
from a few examples and a
little bit of experience
with rewards, what the task is.
And you're trying to train
this few-shot policy that
can adapt with a small
amount of experience.
Now, today, we'll
be kind of building
on some of these concepts
and trying to not just train
a policy to do multiple tasks
but to actually string together
behaviors for multiple tasks
into a longer horizon task.
So this is where we're
going to be talking
about where hierarchy might
be helpful for solving
long-horizon tasks.
And then we'll be
talking about some
of the key design choices
behind hierarchical imitation
and reinforcement
learning methods,
including how to represent
skills and goals, when
to move on from one
goal or task to another,
and the supervision for
the different levels
of the hierarchy.
And then lastly, we'll go
through a couple examples
of what these systems could
actually look like because there
are a variety of
different ways that you
could design these sort
of hierarchical systems.
So the task that we'll
be talking about today
are long-horizon tasks.
And by long-horizon
tasks, I mean
tasks that take a
while to complete
and might consist of a
number of different subtasks
or a number of
different steps that you
need to take in some
sort of sequence or order
in order to complete
it successfully.
So this could be something
like cooking a meal.
It could be for a robot
system, for an LLM agent.
It could be trying to fix a bug
that's causing a neural network
training loss to explode.
For an autonomous vehicle, it
could be driving to Yosemite.
For a different LLM, it
could be giving feedback
on a long report.
And for these
tasks, you can think
about how there are
oftentimes different steps
that you need to complete.
Some of those steps might be
interdependent on one another,
where it makes sense to
do one before the other.
And other tasks
might be something
where they're less
interdependent,
and it's actually OK to
do those in parallel.
These are really hard problems
for AI systems to solve,
in general.
There's a number of
reasons for that.
So the first is
that when you are
doing a task that
takes a long time,
you're visiting a large
number of states along the way
to get there.
And every new state
that you visit,
you need to be able
to make decisions for.
So you basically just have
a much broader distribution
that your policy needs
to be successful on.
There's also a lot of different
opportunities to make mistakes.
And if you make a
mistake, you need
to be able to recover
from that mistake,
if it's something that you
can actually recover from.
And separate from
mistakes, there's
also just opportunities
to get stuck.
For example, if there's
one kind of mistake
that might, for
example, not lead
you to actually make
progress on the task.
And if you're not
making progress,
then you'll actually just end
up in the same state again.
And you'll keep on making that
same mistake over and over again
and essentially just get
stuck at performing the task.
And these kinds of
mistakes are particularly
gnarly because when you end
up in the same state again,
your policy will keep on
deterministically staying
in that state and
never making forward
progress towards the goal.
And then what's the main
idea behind hierarchy?
So we've talked about multi-task
policies, where you have some--
actually, let me draw
this further to the right.
We have some policy that
takes as input some state.
Maybe the state
at some timestep.
And it also takes as input
some task or some goal.
I'm going to write
this as g for now
because this task
or goal could take
a number of different forms.
And this is passed
into your policy
to produce actions that
are trying to address
that particular goal.
The idea for trying to
solve long-horizon tasks
is if we have a policy that can
do a number of different things.
Then we could try
to break up a bigger
task into different
subtasks and then
use one policy to actually tell
this policy what task it should
be doing at any
given point in time.
So for example, you could
have another policy here
that's actually outputting
the goals to be doing.
And this policy should
also have information
about the state as input so
that it knows where it is
and what goal makes sense
for the agent to do.
And then optionally, this is
often called a low-level policy,
or we'll use pi LL to refer.
This is the low-level policy.
This is doing shorter tasks.
And we can refer to this as
a high-level policy that's
outputting goals for the
low-level policy to accomplish.
And this policy,
it can have a task.
Sorry.
I wrote this as low level.
This should be high level.
If you want your
policy to be able to do
multiple long-horizon tasks,
then this high-level policy
could also have some sort of
task descriptor as input as
well, or some sort
of goal as input.
And so we, for example, could
have goal high level as input
to this policy, if you
want to be completing
not just one long-horizon task
but multiple long-horizon tasks.
Like not just
driving to Yosemite
but also being able
to drive to the Grand
Canyon or LA or Seattle
or something like that.
And the kind of crux
underlying this idea
is that if we can break up a
really long task into smaller
parts, then we might be able
to better address the problem.
And say, for example,
your long-horizon task
is to bake a cheesecake.
This is a really,
really hard problem.
And if you just tried to train
a policy like a robot policy
to output motor commands
for doing this task,
it's really hard to figure
out what you should be doing
at any given point in time.
But if you're just starting
out, you can think about, OK,
what's the first step
for accomplishing this?
Maybe you need to
buy ingredients.
Then what's the first step
of buying ingredients?
Well, maybe you need
to go to the store.
And how do you get to the store?
Well, maybe you need
to walk to the door.
To walk to the door,
you might take a step.
How do you take a step?
You might contract a muscle.
And so you can basically
break down a bigger task
into a much smaller task.
And these smaller tasks are
a lot easier to train systems
to do.
And if you can train systems
to do the smaller tasks,
then you can try to compose
them with a higher-level policy
to be able to accomplish
that more challenging task.
So what we can do is for the
"bake a cheesecake" task,
we could pass this with a state
or observation into a high-level
policy, which is going to
predict an intermediate step,
like for example, go to the
store or go to the door.
And then that intermediate
step, along with the state
or observation, will be
passed to the low-level policy
to predict an action.
Now, a couple notes here.
So one note is that
this low-level policy--
this needs to be acting
at the original frequency.
So if you're
controlling a robot,
maybe this is
operating at 20 hertz.
If you're controlling
a language model,
then this is going to be
outputting word by word.
Whereas the
high-level policy, it
could actually predict goals
for the low-level policy
at a coarser timescale.
And so, for example, it
could be outputting goals
after you've completed a
paragraph for a language model
or after you've completed that--
like going to the
store, for example.
It could then give a new
goal for the low-level policy
to perform.
And so we have a
high-level policy that
predicts intermediate goals.
And then the low
level policy tries
to accomplish those intermediate
goals by predicting actions.
Typically, the
low-level policy is
operating at a higher frequency
than the high-level policy.
And I should note that--
I'll refer to these as
kind of goals or subtasks.
There's a number of
other names for these
as well, like skills or options.
You could also think about
these as high-level actions.
So these are actions but
for a different policy
that's operating at a
higher level of abstraction
than the original policy.
And then the other
thing here is that--
this is like a
two-level hierarchy,
but you could also imagine
having more than two levels
of hierarchy as well.
And for example, the baking a
cheesecake, you could have--
maybe one level
of hierarchy could
be things like go to the store,
buy the things, bring them back.
And a different
level of hierarchy
might actually be controlling,
like the motors on a robot,
in order to accomplish
those tasks.
And then once we have
this hierarchical policy,
how do we actually roll it
out if we can do these things?
So specifically, if we're at,
say, we'll start at t equals 1,
then the first
step is to predict.
Or another way to think about
predicting a goal is planning.
We're trying to think forward.
What is the next step
that we should do?
So we could try to plan a goal.
And this will be by sampling
from our high-level policy based
off of the current state and
optionally some high-level goal.
And then we'll be
repeatedly sampling
from our low-level policy.
And so we could repeat.
First sample, an action from the
low-level policy using this goal
as input.
So sample a from high low level,
with the state and this goal--
the goal from the
high level as input.
And then we'll actually
execute that action
and get the next state.
So basically at that
point, we'll then--
t will now become t plus 1.
And we'll observe St. Then again
with the same goal as before.
But the new state will then
be sampling a new action,
repeating this process.
And then at some
point after we have--
and we'll talk a
little bit about how we
decide when to get a new goal.
But when we have decided
that we're either
done with the goal or
enough time has passed,
then we'll move back to step one
to re-plan a new goal based off
of the latest state.
Yeah.
So let's walk through this, and
then I'll get to your question
in a minute.
So is there some initial state
or observation, plan a new goal?
Until a new goal
is selected, we're
going to execute a
predicted action according
to our low-level policy based
off of that predicted goal.
And then we'll observe
a new observation.
Now, why might hierarchy help?
Which I think is getting
at your question.
There's a couple
reasons for this.
So the first is
that typically we're
going to be training this
low-level policy to reach
goals and this high-level policy
to maximize rewards or reach
some high-level goals.
And this means that the
objective for this policy
is different than the overall
objective of completing
the long-horizon task.
And so this is actually
getting different supervision.
And this intermediate
supervision signal
for how to complete
intermediate goals or tasks
can be useful for guiding
the policy towards completing
the long-horizon task.
So you can think
about it potentially.
It depends on the setup,
but you can think about it
as a way to leverage
intermediate supervision.
Now you could always have
intermediate supervision
when training a big, flat
policy as well, where
you give it shaped
rewards, and you give it
rewards for completing
individual subtasks.
But compared to that,
the other difference
here is that this
low-level multi-task policy
is going to be able to more
explicitly share knowledge
across the different subtasks.
So because, for example,
it has this goal as input,
it's targeting a
particular subtask.
And if two subtasks are
quite similar to one another,
then this policy will be able
to share data across those tasks
in order to more
efficiently learn,
compared to if you
were just to try
to train a single policy
across the long-horizon task.
In reinforcement learning,
specifically, you
can also think about benefits
in terms of exploration.
And in particular, when
this high-level policy
is proposing goals
to reach, that's
structuring the
exploration process
to encourage it to explore not
just in the original action
space but also in this
higher-level goal space.
And lastly, there can also be
sometimes practical benefits
as well.
So, for example,
if you're thinking
about this task of making
a cheesecake, for example,
you might need to be reasoning
through the steps for how
to do that.
And if you have a
single policy, then you
need to reason
through those steps
every single timestep
with that flat policy.
So if your robot is
operating at 20 hertz,
for example, you're going to
be reasoning through like, what
is the next thing
I should be doing
and the way to get there with my
action at every single timestep?
Where here, we can run
this reasoning computation
at a lower frequency than
the low-level policy.
So that can be kind
of a practical benefit
in terms of compute costs.
Yeah.
So the question is, can we
elaborate on the first point,
and how the supervision
for the low-level policy
is different for the
high-level policy?
So the high level policy--
it's goal is to complete
the long-horizon task.
So it's goal is to
bake the cheesecake,
and it gets rewards when
the cheesecake is baked.
The low-level policy--
it gets rewards
for completing
intermediate subtasks.
And so when it, for example,
finds the ingredients, preheat
the oven, that
sort of thing, it's
getting rewards for
completing those tasks.
And that intermediate
supervision
guides it towards completing
the long-horizon task.
Yeah.
So the question is,
what if you need to be
doing multiple tasks at once?
So in that case, unless your
low-level agent can has--
I don't know-- 10 arms or
something or can output things
in parallel, you do need to
pick some order for that.
Now, the goal of the
high-level policy
is to figure out whether
that order matters or not.
And so if it figures out that
the order is really important,
then it will get rewards.
It will be better able to
predict those goals if it
predicts the correct order.
In other circumstances, if
the order doesn't matter,
then it should be able to
learn that and figure out
that it doesn't really
matter, and it'll just
pick one arbitrarily.
Now, there's also a
question of whether or not
we actually need multiple
policies in order
to get some of these benefits.
And on the last slide, we
talked about the benefits
of what you might get with
a hierarchical approach
versus just what's called a flat
policy with no hierarchy, which
is the typical path in the
long-horizon task and the state
and predict the action.
There's actually also
an intermediate approach
that you can take as
well, that actually
retains a lot of the
benefits of hierarchy
and actually, in some ways,
has a lot of the same design
choices, which is something
that's a little bit like chain
of thought in language models,
if you're familiar with that--
which is that if you have
some long-horizon task,
you could have the policy
first reason through what goal
or what subtask it should be
completing and then predict
the low-level action.
So this is kind of combining
these two policies into one.
But now you're just
predicting them in sequence.
You're first predicting the
goal and then the action.
This sort of
approach can actually
retain a fair number
of the benefits,
so it can benefit
from the same sort
of intermediate supervision.
It also might have some
practical downsides.
So this doesn't
have the benefits
of the kind of practical
computational benefits
of separating them into
two because then you still
have to run this at
the full frequency.
There isn't entirely
a conclusion
yet empirically on
whether this is just
as good as a
hierarchical approach.
And you could imagine
that there might
be benefits in terms of
sharing some knowledge
with low-level policies versus
with a combined approach.
So this is an open
area of research
on whether or not you
could just do this.
And the only really
conclusive downside
would be the computational
upside of having reasoning
at a lower frequency than taking
actions for the first one.
So the question is, why is
having intermediate supervision
helpful?
There's a couple reasons.
So if you're in a
reinforcement learning setting
and your goal is to
make a cheesecake
and you only get rewards when
the cheesecake is baked versus
not, then those rewards are
going to be really sparse
and not actually
allow you to progress.
The second is that even if you--
say, you're in an imitation
learning setting, like you're
just predicting actions,
imitating actions for
making a cheesecake,
then sometimes if the
policy isn't explicitly
thinking about what part of
that task it might be doing,
it might oscillate between
different subtasks,
especially if it doesn't have
a history of past observations.
So there's also even benefits
in imitation learning settings
as well.
So now let's dive into
some of the design choices.
This will also start to answer
some of the questions that
have come up as well.
So the first is that
we've abstractly
been talking about
these different goals,
and we need to think about
how to actually represent
those different goals.
And I'm actually want to start
with this as an exercise for you
all to think about what
different representations might
make sense for
different problems.
And so I'll give you a few
different example problems.
And then the goal for
you is to think through
for that particular problem.
What would be kind of
sensible intermediate steps
for the agent?
And how would you
actually represent
those different
intermediate steps?
So the first task
is a robot that
wants to learn how to cook
Italian dishes like focaccia.
What would the intermediate
steps for those cooking tasks
look like if it needs to
control its motors to complete
that task and the
representation for that?
The second one is maybe you're
developing an autonomous driving
bike, and you want it to break
down navigation and biking
to various locations on campus.
The third is a
language model that
is drafting legal briefs,
which is also a rather
complex and involved process.
And then the last
is maybe a web agent
that needs to plan and book
one week vacations for users.
So I'll give you a couple
minutes to pick one of these.
Discuss with your neighbor what
intermediate goals would look
like.
And then we'll come
back and discuss.
Does anyone want to share
what they discussed?
Cool.
Yeah.
So for number two,
one way that you
could address it is the
different intermediate goals
could be like waypoints towards
that particular goal location
that you want to reach.
And then the representation for
that could be GPS coordinates.
And the reward for
the low-level policy
would be like, how close are
you to those GPS coordinates?
So yeah, something
like that makes sense?
Anyone else want to share
either for that problem
or a different problem?
Yeah, cool.
So for the fourth one,
you could-- there's
a few different ways you
could think about it.
You could think about it as
intermediate goals or booking
day one, booking day
two, booking day three.
Or you could have a more coarse,
defined approach where you're
booking travel, booking--
I don't know-- hotels
or whatever, and then
specific activities.
One other part of this
that I would imagine you
would need to do is just
generally figuring out
what does the user want
from their vacation.
And so doing high-level
research first.
And that could be also
an intermediate goal
as part of completing the task.
Did anyone pick one or three?
So the intermediate goals are
things like opening the cabinet,
beating the eggs, and then the
representation for those goals.
All right.
Didn't quite get to that.
So a few things
that you could do
for the representation
for that is it
could just be a
natural language.
So it could be literally
the string beat the eggs
or open the cabinet.
If, for example, if
you're cooking something
where you want to look
in a particular way,
you can even have an image as an
intermediate goal representation
as well, saying like, I want
the bread to look like this,
or yeah, that sort of thing.
So can imagine multimodal
goal representations as well.
So one of the
things that I wanted
to convey with this exercise
is that oftentimes the goal
representation that
you might pick likely
depends on the particular domain
or the particular problem.
For example, like for
biking, it might be
something like GPS coordinates.
Whereas for cooking,
it might be language.
For booking a vacation, it
might also be in language.
There might also be images
involved and so forth.
And in terms of what these
representations might look like,
oftentimes you'll
want it to be--
if you're developing something
for many different subtasks,
you want it to be
fairly expressive.
If you're trying to cook
lots of different meals--
natural language is something
that's like quite expressive
and can describe a number of
different low-level behaviors.
Ideally, it also
has some structure.
And so for example, if your
different goals are just
do task subtask
one, do subtask two,
it's going to be hard
for your low-level policy
to figure out how those
relate to one another.
Whereas if you have something
like GPS coordinates,
then two GPS coordinates that
are very close to each other
are going to have
similar actions.
And that sort of
structure will make
the learning problem a lot
easier for the low-level policy.
And then the third is also
picking an appropriate level
of abstraction.
So for the biking
task, for example,
you can have a level
of abstraction that's
like potentially two low level.
So you could have something
that's kind of pedal--
I don't know-- current,
like exact velocity
for the next second.
You could also have
something too high level,
which is like go to the quad
or something, which might not
be particularly helpful in terms
of breaking the problem down
into smaller steps.
And choosing the right
level of abstraction
is often somewhat tricky and
can also be domain dependent,
depending on the
particular kind of details
of the problem and
the application area.
So the question is,
should we also abstract
the state space for each layer?
This depends on whether or
not you have access to that--
that sort of abstraction layer.
Let's see.
Oftentimes, even for
the high-level policy,
it's helpful for it to
have all of the information
about the current state in order
to make even high-level goal
predictions.
But yeah, there are some
things that you can do.
You could, for example,
ask a language model
to summarize the high-level
information about a state
and have a high-level
policy use that information.
But generally, in
practice, you'll
often use the same low level,
like the full-state information.
You don't lose too much
from doing that as well.
Now let's talk a little
bit about the supervision
for each level.
And for this, I think it's
helpful to consider an example.
So let's consider an example
where you're making pasta.
And I chose this to be slightly
simpler long-horizon task.
And you could imagine there
being a few steps involved
for doing this.
And we can abstractly
think about the state
space for this task and reaching
different intermediate steps
for this.
Let's see.
Let's say that this is your
initial state distribution.
And the steps for
making pasta is
that you'll need to get
out a pot and pasta, so
some ingredients.
You'll need to boil the water.
And you also need to pour the
pasta into the boiling water.
Maybe there's also
a straining step,
but maybe we can
skip that for now.
And we can think about the--
imagine the set of
states where you have--
for example, you
have taken out a pot.
So find a pot before actually
like putting any water into it.
You could have
some states, where
you've now have boiled the
water, another set of states
where you have found the pasta,
and then some other states where
the pasta is cooked.
If we have our
low-level policy, it's
going to be trying
to figure out like,
how do I take actions to
reach these kinds of states?
And then the
high-level policy is
trying to predict, if
I'm in a given state,
what command should I use to
tell the low-level policy what
to do?
And generally, as we've
talked about a bit
before, for the
low-level policy,
it's going to be getting
rewards that are based off
of the low-level tasks.
And the goal of
something like this
would be something where you're
moving towards finding a pot.
Maybe then you try
to boil the water.
Then you try to find the pasta.
And then you try
to cook the pasta.
Now, one thing that we talked
about a little bit before is--
so this is actually deviating
from this example a little bit--
we'll come back to it--
is we could also just
train the high-level policy
and the low-level
policy end to end
without any intermediate
goal representation.
Just for example,
we'd have some sort
of latent goal representation.
That's just the activations
of the neural network.
And we could train
all of these just
for the high-level task and the
rewards of completing the task.
Now, one important thing
that is good to know about
of the supervision is that if
you do that, that's basically
just a flat policy with a
particular architecture that
has some sort of activations
when you feed in the observation
twice.
You just think about
that as basically
a single neural
network architecture.
That's basically the
same as a flat policy.
And the reason why it's
important to recognize this is,
is that when designing
these kinds of systems,
it's important to think about
where the benefits are coming
from, whether it's coming
from additional supervision,
whether it's coming from
structured exploration.
And if you don't think
carefully about this,
you could end up in
a situation where
intuitively if you haven't
thought about it, it's like, oh.
Ideally, my high-level
policy will do this.
My low-level policy will do this
without actually seeing benefits
compared to just
naively training
things with a single policy.
For those of you that
are doing research,
it's also just generally
something that's good to do
in any kind of research
because you never really know
if the systems that you're
developing or the methods that
you're developing are going
to improve over some existing
state-of-the-art method.
And if you're very
honest with yourself
about what might go wrong
and why might not actually
see benefits from your
new idea, then you
can think more critically
about what sorts of things
will actually improve
the final results.
Cool.
So supervising each level.
So we have the low-level policy.
And the low-level
policy will be trained
to accomplish that goal,
not the original task.
And so when you're passing
in the string of "find pot,"
it's going to be getting
a reward that is trying
to maximize reward for getting
to the states where you found
the pot.
And the high-level policy--
its goal is to
predict the subtasks
so that you end up in the final
state of the pasta being cooked.
So this is kind of trying to
accomplish the original goal.
Now there's a couple
of things that can be
a little bit tricky about this.
So say that you're
training these separately
and say that you've trained--
you could, for example,
think about training a policy
to find the pot,
and maybe you've
gotten to a good policy that's
really good at finding the pot
and getting to the
state really reliably.
And then maybe for example,
when you train the policy
for finding the pasta.
If you weren't exactly
careful with how you did this,
maybe you would think about,
OK, maybe I could actually just
start from this
state and also try
to find the pasta from
this state over here.
And that's not taking into
account that actually when
it's finding the
pasta, according
to the high-level policy, if
the high-level policy actually
wanted it to find the pasta
after boiling the water when
you're at the stove.
Then when you actually
try to string together
this low-level policy with the
low-level policy for these two.
It'll actually then
struggle to transition
from going to the stove over
to finding where the pasta is.
And this is basically like
a mismatch when you're
training these modular systems.
And you're training them
completely independently.
You might not actually get a
system that works effectively
if they're not actually at
some point connected together
and trained such that this
skill is starting from states
where the high-level
policy will actually
start commanding that task.
And so essentially when you're
training the low-level policy--
so you have your
low-level policy actions,
given states and goals.
You want this policy to
work for the set of states
where the high-level
policy is going to command
this particular goal.
Another way to think
about this is that--
and I guess the other
thing here is also
you want it to be able to
pick the goals that actually
the high-level
policy would predict.
So for different
distributions of goals
and different distributions
of states, ideally,
that low level policy
would work for whatever
states and goals the
high-level policy will output.
Now, if we haven't actually
learned a high-level policy yet,
this puts things in a bit
of a tricky situation.
And likewise for the
high-level policy,
if we assume that our low-level
policy is really great,
then we might not
realize that it actually
has some deficiencies and
that we need to, for example,
continue to command
something in certain states
until you've actually reached a
state that a different skill can
operate in.
Yeah.
So if the low-level policy
works from particular sequences
of states, then the
high-level policy
can learn that it should
walk the low-level policy
through those states.
So you don't necessarily
need your low-level policy
to work from every state.
It just needs to work for
the state-goal combinations
that the high-level policy
is going to command.
Now, you might have
a situation where,
say, that your
low-level policy knows
how to do something like this.
So it knows how to
go from here to here.
It knows how to go
from here to here
and maybe knows how to
go from here to here,
like with some boiled water.
Then you might have
some sort of gap
where to actually
find the pasta,
you need to go back
to these states.
And if you don't have
a command or some way
to get from here to
here, then you're
going to basically have
a gap in the states
that you're visited in.
The high-level policy
will struggle to actually
get to this state here.
And so basically,
one way to think
about it is you need to make
sure that there's at least some
overlap in the states from
one skill to the next.
And ideally, that
overlap has some buffer.
Because if, for example, when
you're trying to find the pasta,
it only works if
you're standing exactly
in front of the boiled
water and not if you're
like a little bit to the right.
Then if your policy ends up
deciding to boil the water,
standing a little bit
to the right of it,
then you'll get a brittle
final result where
it will struggle in that case.
I guess one way
to think about it
is that if this
low-level policy only
works from this
part of the states
where the water is being boiled
and the high-level policy gets
you here, or the previous
low-level policy gets you here,
then you're going to have a
little bit of a gap between here
and here.
And that sort of gap can
lead to brittle performance
on the full long-horizon task.
Yeah.
So the question is, does it
have to be a fixed sequence?
And can you learn
if one sequence
is more efficient than another?
Yeah.
So absolutely, the
high-level policy
can actually decide which
sequence it wants to do,
and that sequence might depend
on what's the most efficient.
It might also depend on
where the low-level policy is
most successful.
And so one of the reasons why
I wanted to pick this example
is actually these two steps
can be done in any order.
And the high-level policy could
decide that when you're here,
it actually wants to
command you to go here.
And as long as the
low-level policy
knows how to find the
pasta from these states,
then that might be
more efficient overall.
There's also worlds
where maybe this would
be more efficient because maybe
while you're boiling the water,
you're just waiting.
And you can find the
pasta in the meantime.
And so I guess there's also a
pouring water that-- and turning
on the stove and so forth.
So there's more steps involved.
But yeah, the high-level
policy can decide
which order it wants to take.
So generally the
way to address this
is that you can first train
them potentially completely
separately.
But it's important for
at least one policy
to be adapted to the other.
And ideally, even both could be
jointly adapted with each other
to optimize reward, or optimize
some complete objective.
Cool.
One other side note,
I guess, that I
think is worth
mentioning is that the--
even for problems that are not
traditionally LLM problems--
LLMs are actually often
pretty good at some
of the higher-level reasoning
that you might want to do.
And so, for example, if you know
that you want to cook pasta,
if you ask a language model
what are the steps involved
with that, oftentimes, they
can actually give you that.
And so this is one way
where you can actually
train the high-level policy
completely separately
from the low-level policy and
then potentially fine-tune them
because the language
model, for example,
might not know which order the
low-level policy is best suited
for, or other things
about the capabilities
of the low-level policy.
And so that sort of
adaptation process,
even though language models
are pretty good at this,
that sort of adaptation
process is really important.
Also, if a robot is in
front of a coffee machine
and you ask the robot to
get some coffee for you,
if the language model doesn't
actually pay attention
to that image, it might
tell the robot like, oh,
can you go out and buy coffee
at Starbucks or something?
And the robot might not have
that sort of affordance,
that sort of ability to do that.
And so adapting
these two together,
that's another example
where adapting these two
high-level and
low-level policies
together is quite important.
The last key design choice that
we haven't talked about yet
is when to move from
one task to another.
So we outlined
this process here,
and we didn't really spend
that much time thinking about
like, how long do
you repeat sampling
from your low-level policy
to accomplish a goal?
And essentially,
it's how often do we
requery a new goal from
the high-level policy
to pass through the
low-level policy.
So basically, yeah,
this step right here.
So there's two natural
options for this.
The first natural option is to
requery the high-level policy
whenever the low-level policy
has completed the goal.
So when it has boiled
the water, that's
when you tell it to go find
the pasta, for example.
And the way that this
would look like is--
at this point, your
low-level policy not only
needs to predict action but
also needs to predict whether
or it's successfully
completed the task.
And this could be either with
some sort of binary indicator
or through some sort
of progress indicator.
You can think about this
not done as a success
classifier for the task.
And then the other option that's
a bit simpler but maybe less
elegant, in some ways,
is just to simply requery
the high-level policy after
some fixed number of timesteps.
So maybe you query the
low-level policy at 50 hertz,
and you query the high-level
policy once every second.
So then you would be querying
the high-level policy
after 50 timesteps.
So there's pros and cons of
each of these two options.
For the first case where
we're doing something
after we've completed a
goal, this is actually ideal.
If you were to do
this well, this
should be the most
compute efficient
because you're waiting
for the low-level policy.
You don't need to
rethink how you're
doing the task while the
low-level policy is executing.
There's a couple of things that
are tricky about this though.
The first is that
it can actually
be hard to estimate when
you're done with a task.
It's definitely not
trivial to do this.
And the second is
that you actually
need to account for mistakes
that require actually
redoing some past goal.
So for example,
if you are trying
to organize some things on a
table, you go grab something,
and then you accidentally
drop it on the ground.
Your subgoal should no longer
be like, put that object
on the table, and
instead it should be
to pick it up off the ground.
And this means that
actually you need
to now estimate not
just when you're
done but also whether
or not you've actually
exited the states in which
that subtask makes sense.
Then going back to the
fixed number of timesteps,
this is less ideal because we're
going to be probably wasting
some compute, and
there's going to be
a trade-off between
spending more compute,
thinking through what
the next goal should be,
versus if this n is too long.
Then you're going to be
delayed in transitioning
to the new goal, where your
agent will be-- for example,
maybe it's found the pot.
It's taken out the pot, and
it's waiting for a new goal.
If n is too long,
it's just going
to be sitting there with the
pot because it's like, OK,
I found the pot.
And that's the goal
that it's getting.
And there'll be some
delay before it then
moves on to actually
finding the pasta
or pouring water into the pot.
So this trade-off between
how long n should be.
Generally, because you don't
want these really long delays,
you'll pick n to be fairly
small or fairly frequent.
But when n is
smaller, you're then
going to be placing more burden
on your high-level policy
because it needs to be making
accurate goal predictions more
frequently on more states.
And you'll be spending
more compute as well.
So both of these
have pros and cons.
In general, if we wanted to
think about how these pros
and cons relate
to each other, we
can think about how
these pros and cons lead
to different
downstream performance.
And with regard to
estimating when you're done
and accounting for
mistakes, if you actually
make a mistake in estimating
when you're done, then
you could actually
end up in a situation
where the agent is
perpetually stuck.
If it thinks that it's not
done but it is actually done,
then it will actually
just stay in that state
because the low-level policy
will keep on predicting this--
won't actually be making
any more further progress
on the task.
So this actually is a
pretty rough outcome
for these kinds of errors,
even if they're infrequent.
And then for option two,
if you make a mistake
in predicting the
subtask because you're
querying the high-level
policy more frequently,
this also has bad outcome, which
is that the low-level policy
might stop making
progress on the final task
and might be taking the
wrong actions for n steps
until you get hopefully a
more accurate goal prediction.
And generally, between
these two things,
these errors are more fatal.
And as a result, typically, a
lot of the hierarchical systems
out there opt for choosing
option two because
of the simplicity
and because some
of the mistakes that the
high-level policy might make
when it's queried
more frequently
are less fatal than
mistakes with regard
to estimating when you're
done and at what subtask,
whether or not you should
re-account for past goals.
It's also worth mentioning
that you could potentially
combine these, where you
try to estimate progress.
But then if it's been
a long period of time,
then you're re-query anyway.
But yeah, the takeaway is
that, generally, option two
is typically what people
do, where you just query
at a fixed lower frequency.
Cool.
So let's look at
some example systems.
And I guess one thing
that I'll mention
is that hierarchy is
pretty popular these days.
So here are four
systems that we're all
announced in the last
five months, four months.
And they actually all
use hierarchical systems.
So these are all fairly
long horizon tasks,
where you're cleaning a
bedroom, handing over objects,
and pouring them or
putting them into bins,
putting away objects
into a fridge,
putting fruit into bowls.
And if you look at the
architectures for these things,
they all have some
higher-level model
that's predicting
intermediate goals
and some lower-level model that
is predicting low-level actions.
These are in robotics domains.
Likewise in language
model domains,
things like chain of thought,
where you're reasoning
through intermediate steps.
And then actually outputting
tokens for those steps
is also really popular for
completing more challenging
language tasks.
Cool.
So I want to cover a few
examples of these systems,
and I picked
examples that I think
illustrate a few different
design choices that are helpful
and actually have comparisons
on those design choices
that elucidate some of
the benefits of one design
choice versus another.
So let's start with talking
about hierarchical imitation
learning systems.
And we'll start with
language subgoals.
And let's first talk about
what the data would look
like for training a hierarchical
imitation learning system
with language subgoals.
This will be kind of
a real robot example.
What the data looks
like is actually
it's going to use data of a
long-horizon demonstration
of completing the complete
long-horizon task.
And so in this case, the
task is to make trail mix
and put the trail
mix into a bag.
And with this long-horizon
demonstration for the full task,
it will then be segmented
with language labels
for each segment.
And in this case, the
segments in the data
can have a variable length.
If, for example,
the robot trajectory
looks something like this,
then you might have--
the first subtask is
something like this.
The second subtask
is maybe shorter.
The third subtask
is maybe longer.
So you'll have variable
frequency in the data,
but the actual system will later
be using a fixed frequency where
it's requiring more frequently
than the typical segment
length in the data.
So these are different
language labels.
These labels could either be
recorded during data collection,
where you're actually saying,
I'm going to pick up the bag
and then do a demonstration
of picking up the bag.
Then say, I'm going to
pick up the metal scoop,
do a demonstration
of that in sequence,
or you can do it
post-hoc where you just
collect the full demonstration.
And then with a
labeling interface label
like, this segment is
picking up the bag.
This segment is picking
up the metal scoop.
This segment is getting
M&Ms and so forth.
So we have segmented
demonstrations
with the associated
language command.
Here's another example of
what this would look like.
And this shows that one segment
might be longer for picking up
a slice of cheese,
a different segment
might be shorter for putting
the cheese on the bread
and so forth.
Cool.
And then once we
have this data, we'll
train a high-level policy
and a low-level policy
with imitation learning.
And the high-level policy will
be outputting the language
labels from the observations.
And the low level will
be taking the language
labels and the observations
and predicting the actions.
So what this looks like
is an image observation.
So an RGB image passes it
into a high-level policy
that's trained to predict
the language label.
And then you'll have a low-level
policy that takes the language,
in addition to the observations.
In this case, the work chooses
to use not just RGB images
but also joint angles as
input to the low-level policy.
And generally, it's
OK to have actually
this sort of mismatch between
observations for the high-level
and the low-level policy.
And then the low-level policy
outputs joint commands.
And the low-level policy
operates at 50 hertz.
And I can't remember
the exact frequency
of the high-level
policy, but I think
it's something around 1 hertz.
Cool.
So that's the general setup.
Now we also learned
about DAgger.
And you can think
about if we just
do imitation learning
on the offline data,
we might have issues
where we're training these
somewhat independently,
although the data is at least
of the full long-horizon task.
And we could actually use
DAgger with these systems
on both the low-level policy
and the high-level policy.
Now, one thing
that's pretty cool
is that actually for
the high-level policy,
we can actually update
the high-level policy
with language supervision.
And so DAgger on the
high-level policy
is actually in language
space, not in joint space.
And so in principle, you can
do DAgger on both low level
and high level.
In this particular
approach, if you
were to do it on the high level
with freezing the low level,
you would be running the
policy, the full system.
And then you would
then type or speak
a language command that
is going to override
the high-level policy and
then continue collecting data.
And then at some point,
you might give control back
to the high-level policy.
And then from there, you
can fine-tune and actually
do gradient steps on data that
has these kinds of language
interventions to actually
fine-tune the high-level policy.
And when you do this together
with the high-level policy
and the low-level policy
acting as one system,
then you can actually
adapt the high-level policy
to deficiencies in
the low-level policy.
So, for example, if there's
one language command
that the low-level policy
makes a mistake on,
then you could actually issue
some corrections to help
compensate for that mistake.
So yeah.
I guess to summarize, we can
train the high-level policy
and the low-level policy,
both with imitation,
and then freeze the
low-level policy
and update the high level policy
with DAgger by supervising
on language corrections.
And so as a video of
what this looks like,
these yellow commands
are showing the output
of the high-level policy.
And then the robot motions
are showing the output
of the low-level policy.
So at the beginning, the
high-level policy is saying,
pick up spoon.
The robot picks up the spoon,
move the spoon towards me.
So then it says I
want some peanuts.
So then the low-level
policy scoops peanuts.
Then the high-level policy says
move the scoop into the bag.
The low-level policy
starts to do that.
At this point, you'll
actually notice that the robot
is about to make a mistake.
And so that's when
you can intervene.
And instead of telling the
robot move the scoop in the bag,
because it seems like the
low-level policy isn't going
to do that correctly, you
could then intervene and say,
move the scoop into the bag.
Or instead of saying
move the scoop,
you say move the
left arm to the left,
go higher, move the
scoop into the bag, then.
And so these user
commands are overriding
the high-level policy.
And then at this point,
you can give control back
to the high-level policy.
And the high-level policy
predicts, pour into the bag,
get some banana
chips, and so forth.
So that's what this sort
of DAgger intervention
looks in the high-level space.
And then after you fine-tune
the high-level policy
on those kinds of interventions,
can then self-correct and
know that the low-level policy
is making a mistake,
where it was
about to make the same
sort of mistake again.
And then the high-level policy
says, go higher, and then
move the scoop into the bag to
prevent that sort of mistake.
And so this is an example of the
high-level and low-level policy
adapting together to
account for deficiencies.
Cool.
Now we've talked about
hierarchy versus flat policies.
You could ask.
You can actually
do a comparison.
In this particular
setup, does hierarchy
outperform using a
single flat policy
to do the long-horizon task?
This comparison is actually
from a different research paper,
but it has basically
the same approach.
In terms of task
progress, there's
a 34% improvement
from using hierarchy
versus training a
single policy to do
the full long-horizon
imitation learning task.
And in terms of
following instructions,
there's also a gap.
This is this instruction
accuracy metric.
And you can also
actually compare
DAgger to imitation learning
for the high-level policy.
And you can also
see that there's
an improvement from using
DAgger compared to just using
vanilla imitation learning.
And this is the
improvement that you
get from adopting the
policies together.
Cool.
The nice thing
about hierarchies,
you can do longer horizon tasks.
And so with this full
system, you can, for example,
get the robot to put three
objects into a Ziploc bag, which
is traditionally a
pretty difficult task
to do, especially in one go.
And likewise with
a similar system,
you can also get a robot to--
the high-level command
is clean the bedroom.
And then the
low-level policy will
output things like pick up
shirt, put shirt in basket,
pick up shirt, put
shirt in basket.
And later pick up the
pillow, adjust the blanket,
put the pillow at the top of
the bed, adjust the pillow,
pick up tissue, put the tissue
in the trash can, and so forth.
And so these are
things that are like,
would be very hard to do if you
just train a single flat policy.
So instead of using
language, we could also
use images as that
intermediate representation.
And so what this would
look like is instead
of having the high-level
policy output language,
you would output a goal image.
And so it'd be like,
this is the kind
of an image of what I want you
to accomplish in the future.
In practice, you can
use a generative model,
like an image-editing
model to do
this, that takes as input
the image of the current step
and then edits that to look like
an image at a future timestep
that you want the
robot to achieve.
And then the low-level
policy would no longer
be language conditioned
but would rather
be a goal image
conditioned policy.
And so you can think of this as
a kind of a multi-step inverse
model that takes as
input the current image,
some future image, and
then outputs the actions
that you can take to
get to that goal image.
And then both of these
will be trained again
with imitation learning.
And one of the things
that's pretty nice
is that you no longer need to
segment videos with language
annotations to do this.
You just need the videos
of the long-horizon task.
And to train this
high-level policy,
you can train it on robot
data and predict future images
in the trajectory, like
from 1 second or 5 seconds
into the future, or 10
seconds in the future.
But you could also actually
train this high-level policy
using YouTube videos,
or something like that,
to predict what are future
images that might accomplish
some long-term goal.
And that sort of
unlabeled video data
can be helpful, especially
if data from the robot
is more sparse.
So then an example of
what this looks like
is, say, the task is
to move the wooden bowl
to the top of the table.
You pass that into the
high-level policy that
then generates images, which
are shown with the pink border,
and then that generated subgoal
image with the pink border
is passed as input to the
low-level policy, which
then predicts actions.
And both of these
policies again are
trained with imitation
learning on demonstration data
and potentially also if
for the high-level policy
can be trained on
video data as well.
So this one is putting the
toothpaste in the wooden bowl.
You can see that it generates
these subgoal images of,
for example, holding the
toothpaste above the bowl.
It then reaches that.
Then it generates a subgoal
of lowering the arm.
And so the robot lowers the
arm to complete the task.
And then this last example,
the goal is to open the drawer.
The first subgoal is to put
the gripper on the handle.
Then the next subgoal is to
move the gripper to the right
so that it opens, and so forth.
Another thing that's nice
about this sort of approach
is that if your
policy sees objects
that it's never seen before
that are hard to describe
in language, then you--
obviously, that's something
that it can more easily describe
in images because it can
more easily generalize
across the objects
that it's seeing
and generate pixels
for those images,
if it doesn't know what the
semantic name for that object
is.
Cool.
And then for this
sort of thing, you
can also do a
comparison on like,
is it helpful to include those
unlabeled videos for training
the high-level policy?
And if you only
use robot data, you
get performance that
looks like this.
And if you add videos
of humans for training
the high-level policy, you
get an increase in performance
compared to just using the
robot data to train the policy.
Now, we talked earlier
about how chain of thought
can replace hierarchy.
And there's also approaches
that have developed
chain of thoughts versions
of this, where you can have
some high-level task and
the current observation,
and then actually output either
subgoal images or subtasks.
You can also have
other representations,
like bounding boxes
or waypoints, and then
output the action.
And there are some
recent approaches
from the last one year,
basically, quite recent,
that do something like that.
The other thing to note is that
this is with imitation learning.
And we'll talk
about reinforcement
learning in a minute.
But generally for these
large-scale systems to date,
for the most part, they use
imitation learning more so
than reinforcement learning.
And fine-tuning them with
reinforcement learning
is, in some ways, an
open research question
for like, what is the best
recipe for accomplishing that
at large scales?
It's also a pretty important
research direction,
because if we think about
this slide right here,
the kind of performance
of these systems
is still not super,
super reliable.
I should mention, these are in
pretty challenging situations
with held-out objects that
the robot hasn't seen before.
So it's kind of out of
distribution compared
to what it saw during training.
But if we had a way to train
these with reinforcement
learning, then we
should be able to get
these performances to
be much higher compared
to using imitation learning.
So the question is, like we
talked about personalized
recommendation systems, could
hierarchy be useful for that?
It's not something
that I've seen before.
And generally when
I've seen hierarchy,
it's usually been for pretty
longer-horizon problems
and tasks that are
more complicated.
In language modeling,
it's been used
for math problems,
essentially, and things
where you need to have multiple
steps for completing something.
Yeah.
I could think about it.
So in this case, the
high-level policy
is an image generative model.
And what it does is it's
going to take as input.
It's trained to take
as input, like an image
observation and some high-level
goal, like goal high level.
And then you have
a neural network.
And that neural
network is going to be
trained to output Ot plus k.
And so it's going to
be trained to generate
an image of a future image.
Yeah, trained to
generate a future image.
And you can get this
as if you have videos.
Then you don't need language
annotations to get this image.
In terms of the architecture,
it's using a diffusion model
to generate these images.
That's why you saw
the noise moving
into the image in the
direction of the goal.
Yeah.
So this particular goal might
be on the horizon of like--
I don't know-- a minute.
And this subgoal could
be in the direction,
or it could just be like--
I don't know-- 10 seconds in the
future or something like that.
Yeah.
So in terms of using
image-editing models,
that general sort
of pre-training
can be useful because
it teaches the model how
to generate images, in general.
And then the videos
that are used,
there are actually
videos of people
doing different
tasks that have--
like a single-language
annotation for what the person
is doing in the whole video.
And so those videos
are especially
useful to include because
they're pretty relevant.
If instead you included
random videos on YouTube,
it's a little bit harder.
But it might still
teach it about--
if there's some
future thing, what
are images that could
happen in the future?
And that is useful pre-training
for this kind of task.
Yeah.
So you're asking like, what if
the language isn't accurate?
This is like a sketch
instead of a real image?
So good question.
I guess, first, if you
wanted to use sketches here,
you just want to ideally
train the low-level policy
to be able to use
that sort of thing.
And there are
actually approaches
that have taken images, and you
can convert them into a sketch
and train a low-level
policy to do that.
And you don't actually
necessarily need
this to be a full image.
These are just kind
of, I should mention,
two example representations.
And language is
actually particularly
popular as an intermediate
representation.
But there's lots of other
representations you could use,
including sketches, including--
I don't know-- like a trace of
where you want the robot to go
or something like that.
And then in cases where the
language isn't accurate,
if it is describing
something that's different,
then oftentimes the robot will
then follow that different task
until it's been told to
do something different.
If the high-level policy is
predicting language that is bad,
then the system will suffer.
There are some cases where the
low-level policy might also
ignore the high-level policy.
If you give it
gibberish, it might just
have some sort of, in some
ways, kind of default behavior
because it was trained
to output actions.
For different
states, for example,
if it's like holding
the pasta right here,
regardless of any sort
of language input,
chances are the next action
is actually to pour it.
And so if you don't give
it a language instruction,
or if you give it a noisy
language instruction,
it might still
continue to pour it
just because it knows
that for that state,
typically, that's
what you do next.
Now let's talk briefly about
hierarchical reinforcement
learning.
So when I was bringing
up examples of this,
I think that the hierarchical
imitation learning systems
are quite recent, and I
don't have too many, I think,
exciting examples,
or examples that I
was excited about with regard
to hierarchical reinforcement
learning.
There are a few example
systems that you can look at,
and I think that generally
getting these kinds of systems
to work really well,
potentially on top
of the initialized hierarchical
imitation learning systems--
something that would be,
I think, really exciting
and important to explore.
But generally, in terms of what
has been done and what exists,
you can do hierarchical
reinforcement
learning with trying to
reach different states.
And this could be the
relative target position
of some agents or some objects.
And one cool work
that does this is it
has this four-legged ant
agent that you might have
worked with in homework one.
And its goal is
to get over here.
And to get over
there, it actually
needs to push this
object to the right
and then move there
as a result. And then
there's also this example,
where it needs to get over here.
If it tries to go
directly there,
it will fall in this crevasse.
And instead, it needs
to push and make
a little bridge for
itself and walk over here.
And these are pretty
long-horizon problems,
where if you just try to
take actions greedily,
you won't be able
to get to the goal.
And so the work trained
a goal-conditioned policy
conditioned on goal
states with a reward
of reaching those goal states.
And then it trained a high-level
policy to output goal states.
And those goal states are
the high-level actions.
But it actually also
used hindsight relabeling
for the high-level
policy to actually
relabel high-level actions,
or to relabel the goals
that the high-level
policy should output
in certain circumstances.
And it used an
off-policy algorithm
to train this in order to
allow it to work effectively.
And then another work that
does hierarchical reinforcement
learning uses language goals.
So you could use goal states.
You could also do
language goals.
This trains a
language-conditioned policy.
It uses language relabeling.
So instead of goal
relabeling, just
hindsight relabeling
in language space.
And then the
high-level policy is
trained to output
language, which is actually
a pretty difficult task.
Again, this is a work
that's not too recent.
And so it's from 2019.
And so the tasks are
relatively simple,
where it's trying to be able to
arrange these different objects
in particular order, where you
need to push the green object,
push the red object, the
blue object, and so forth.
Cool.
And then the last thing
that I'll mention is that--
we've talked about
these scenarios, where
you're supervising the low-level
policy to reach some goals
and the high-level policy
to output those goals.
Now, there's, in some ways, a
really cool research direction
of-- instead of
actually supervising
it to do certain goals,
can you actually discover
subtasks or discover
skills that might
be useful without
requiring supervision
on those low-level skills?
And here's one example of a work
that studies that, where it--
in this kind of simple
half-cheetah agent
that you might have also seen
in one of your homeworks.
It's able to learn skills
like backing up, walking
forward, doing I think a
front flip, and so forth.
And then in principle,
if you discovered skills
without supervision,
then you could
try to sequence those
together to do harder tasks.
But this is generally still
an active research area
and something that's pretty
challenging to scale up,
especially in very
large state spaces.
Cool.
That's it.
And next time, we'll be
talking about reinforcement
learning for
robotics, specifically
learning with
autonomy, and a guest
lecture from Ashish Kumar
on the Tesla Optimus team.